Guide to the Joel Garreau Papers, 1954-1994
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Joel Garreau Papers
November 1954-February 1994
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
Joel Garreau,
C0057
33.5 linear feet (65 boxes)
This collection contains research materials for Garreau's books, "Edge City" (1992) and "The Nine Nations of North America" (1981). Materials include newspapers, magazine clippings, contact information, government publications, book excerpts, tapes, annual reports, advertisements, newsletters, essays, interview transcripts, notes, project proposals, pamphlets, fliers, brochures, and other documents.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated by Joel Garreau in 1997-1999.
Biographical Information
Joel Garreau is an American journalist and author. Currently he works as the editor in charge of "cultural revolution" reporting at The Washington Post, as senior fellow at the School of Public Policy at George Mason University, and principal of The Garreau Group, which is "dedicated to the creation of more liveable and profitable urban areas worldwide." He also writes for Wired magazine.
Garreau's work is often compared to that of Jane Jacobs or Ronald J. Oakerson for its focus on urban quality of life and autonomy of urban regions from suburbs and surrounding agricultural areas. His books include, "The Nine Nations of North America" (1981), "Edge City" (1992), and "Radical Evolution: The Promise and Peril of Enhancing Our Minds, Our Bodies -- and What It Means to Be Human" (2005).
Scope and Content
This collection contains research materials and other documents pertaining to Garreau's books, "Edge City" (1992) and "The Nine Nations of North America" (1981). Materials include newspapers, magazine clippings, contact information, government publications, book excerpts, tapes, annual reports, advertisements, newsletters, essays, interview transcripts, notes, project proposals, pamphlets, fliers, brochures, and other documents.
The total volume of the collection is 33.5 linear feet, consisting of 64 document boxes and 1 oversize box. The collection is arranged into 2 series. Series 1 consists of the materials dealing with Garreau's book "Edge City", published in 1992. It contains general "Edge City" files and 11 subsections. The general files cover development in the suburban regions of the Washington, D.C. Metropolitan area; planned communities; edge cities around the world; the location of corporate headquarters; the impact of edge cities on the environment; the economics of urban and suburban development; urban design; real estate development; the availability and use of natural resources; the construction of shopping malls; and housing. Subseries 1.1 deals with Shadow Governments, which are private organizations governing bodies that influence their employees and where they live and work. Subseries 1.2 contains material about the life and work of Til Hazel, a prominent Northern Virginia land developer. Subseries 1.3 deals with land preservation and how land development threatened the environment and historical sites. Subseries 1.4 contains the historical resources used. Subseries 1.5 deals with race and poverty and the effects of development on the poorer regions of both urban and rural areas. Subseries 1.6 covers the transportation and infrastructure issues that arise during the development of edge cities. Subseries 1.7 contains numbers and statistics and the results of various studies many of which focus on office space markets and real estate. Subseries 1.8 contains book excerpts and articles that provide further information about issues in "Edge City". Subseries 1.9 contains transcripts of interviews conducted by Joel Garreau while researching material for "Edge City". Subseries 1.10 is a number of maps. Subseries 1.11 is miscellaneous materials that did not fit in any of the other categories. Series 2 consists of the materials dealing with Garreau's book "The Nine Nations of North America", published in 1981. The general files in series 2 covers regionalism; energy production; religion; journalism; water management; and economics. The first 10 subseries correspond with the first ten chapters of "The Nine Nations": New England, The Foundry, Dixie, Aberrations, The Breadbasket, The Islands, MexAmerica, Ecotopia, The Empty Quarter, and Quebec. Subseries 2.11 deals with the proposed television series based on "The Nine Nations". Series 2.12 is miscellaneous materials that did not fit in any of the other categories.
The collection is especially valuable for its material on the history and development of Northern Virginia. Garreau's chronicling of the growth of Fairfax County and the development of the Tysons Corner area is important for its depth and also for the time in which it was compiled. The "Edge City" material contains extensive files about John "Til" Hazel, a Northern Virginia land developer.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by subject.
Series 1: Edge City, 1959-February 1994 (Boxes 1-52, 65)
Series 2: The Nine Nations of North America, November 1954-February 1987 (Boxes 52-64)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds many other collections of personal papers and organizational records on urban planning and development, particularly in Northern Virginia.
Index Terms
Persons:
Garreau, Joel.; Hazel, Til.
Subjects:
Land use, Urban--United States.; Metropolitan areas--United States.; Real estate development--United States.; Sociology, Urban--United States.; Regionalism--North America
Contents List
- Series 1: Edge City, 1959-February 1994
  Materials pertaining to Garreau's book, "Edge City: Life on the New Frontier" published in 1992. An Edge City is a concentration of business, shopping, and entertainment outside a traditional urban area in what had recently been a residential suburb or semi-rural community.
  - DC Edge Cities, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Ten copies of a map of 'emerging cities' in the Washington Metropolitan Area. Four of the copies have a definition of emerging cites and six of the copies do not. Dave Cook is written in the lower right hand corner of all copies.
  - Edge City Tysons Urban Land Institute, October-November 1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Documents and correspondence about a suburban activity center. Material includes a press release about an Urban Land Institute study about 'Suburban Activity Centers', an executive summary of the study and two maps of the Tysons Corner suburban activity center.
  - Edge City Tycon Towers, June 1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Documents about Tycon Towers, a group of office buildings in Tysons Corner, VA. Documents include newspaper articles, promotional publications for Tycon Towers, notes, a map of the vicinity of Tysons Corner, a listing of available space at Tycon Towers, a building profile and a list of improvements and finishes provided for the tenant.
  - Local Edge City Reston Town Center, December 1986 - June 1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Documents and correspondence about Reston Town Center, VA. Documents include a brochure for Reston Town Center, press releases, concept photographs, New York Times Real Estate Section, Metropolitan Home, and Architect articles about Reston, John G. Tyers' business card, newspaper articles and promotional materials from Reston Land Corporation including a map of Reston and market profiles.
  - Local Edge City Reston, December 1986-February 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Documents about Reston, VA. Material includes a Washington Post article about an election for the Reston Association's Board of Directors, a post article about CIA offices in Reston, a copy of a story about a Reston distillery, a press release and an issue of New Dominion magazine.
  - Local Edge City Prince George's County, August 1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    A Washington Post article about building in Prince George's County.
  - Local Edge City Port America Prince George's County, April-October 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Documents about Prince George's County. Material includes an article from Washington Flyer Magazine about the World Trade Center in Washington, DC and a promotional folder from Associated Financial Corporation containing a statement from the mayor of Glenarden, MD, a statement from the secretary of the Maryland Department of Housing and Community Development, a press release and a promotional pamphlet for Glenarden Apartments.
  - Local Edge City Prince William County, May 1986-February 1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Documents about Prince William County. Material includes notes and Washington Post articles about a mall, real estate, Til Hazel's opinion on Capitol Beltway development and Prince William land development.
  - Local Edge Community Reston Government, June 1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Documents for the Reston, VA government. Material includes A Report to the Reston Community on Governance Options and notes.
  - Local Edge City Clarksburg I-270, January 1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Two newspaper articles, one about development in Clarksburg, MD and the other about National Institute of Health contracts.
  - Local Edge City Rockville Leaf Blowers (Box 1, Folder 11)
    A Washington Post article about leaf blowers and noise limits in Rockville, MD.
  - Edge Cities Tysons Corner, October 1987-April 1990 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Documents about Tysons Corner, VA. Material includes a Tytran newsletter, a business card for E. Wayne Angle, Washington Post articles about the construction of a church and activity at Tysons Corner mall, notes about Tysons Corner, a New York Times article about "The Outer City", an article about Burgville and a table of figures on employment.
  - Local Edge City Silver Spring, February 1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    A Washington Post article about development of Silver Spring, MD.
  - Local Edge City Tysons Urban Land Institute [EDAW], October 1987-May 1988 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Documents and correspondence about Tysons Corner, VA. Material includes EDAW business cards from Michelle Bussard-Jama and Patricia Faux, a New York Times article about "The Outer City", an EDAW firm promotional brochure, a message to Garreau from Janice Stein, a letter to the editor about suburban landscapes, a list of the Tysons Corner suburban activity center physical design team, a Tysons Corner area market report and a press release.
  - Local Edge City Tysons Crime, January 1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    A Washington Post article about automobile theft in Tysons Corner, VA.
  - Local Edge City Reston Mobil, July 1988 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    An article from The Connection about Mobil Corp.'s purchase and development of land in Reston.
  - Local Edge City Silver Spring Redevelopment, November 1988-March 1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Two Washington Post articles, one about development in Silver Spring, the other about planning for traffic.
  - National Edge Cities, Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    A list of "Suburban Activity Centers" or Edge Cities throughout the country.
  - Development of Edge Cities, March 1987-October 1989 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Articles about the development of edge cities. Material includes "The Need For a New Vision for the Development of Large U.S. Metropolitan Areas" by Anthony Downs, "Suburbs: Crisis of Growth" and "Suburbs - Moving Out" by Rick Hampson, an article from US News and World Reports about America's Boom Town, "The Six Types of Urban Village Cores" by Christopher B. Leinberger, a greeting card, New York Times article "Suburbia, Postwar: Like Cities" by Philip S. Gutis and "Beyond the Mall: Suburbs Evolving Into 'Outer Cities'" by William K. Stevens, a Miami Herald article by John Dorschner about new town development and political obstacles, an article from New Dominion about new centers in Northern Virginia, Wall Street Journal articles "The New Boom Towns" by Bernard Wysocki and "Shallow Roots" by Betsy Morris and a USA Today article "Where Urban Sprawl and Suburbs Mesh" about super cities by William Dunn. Theory
  - Development of Edge Cities, November 1989-October 1991 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Articles about the development of edge cities. Material includes "Stressed Out in Suburbia" by Nicholas Lemann, an issue of Design Quarterly, Projects in Architecture, Edge of a City, a report on "The New Urban Region", a letter to Joel Garreau from EM Risse including articles about Clarksburg, an article from Regional Review "Downtown New England" by John Campbell and "The Need For a New Vision for the Development of Large U.S. Metropolitan Areas by Anthony Down. Theory
  - Edge Effects on Nature, December 1988 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Material includes an annotated bibliography from an article from Conservation Biology, "Edge Effects and Conservation of Biotic Diversity" by Larry D. Harris and "A Functional Approach to Estimating Habitat Edge Width for Birds".
  - National Edge City Urban Sprawl Seattle, January 1989 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    A Washington Post article "Seattle's Battle of Urban Sprawl" by O. Casey Corr.
  - National Edge City St. Louis Attractions, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Notes about St. Louis, MO.
  - National Edge City St. Louis, April 1987-August 1988 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Material about St. Louis, including "The Private Places of Saint Louis: A Market Arrangement for Urban Infrastructure" by David T. Beito, notes and a receipt from the Adam's Mark Hotel in St. Louis.
  - International Edge City, January 1992 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Documents about Quebec including "Quebec Through Darkly Tinted Lenses" by Patrick Grady, notes, a letter to Garreau from Andre Anctil, "Canadian Federalism is Objectively Impossible" by Pierre Vadeboncoeur and other articles about Quebecois independence.
  - National Edge City Toronto Real Estate Market Reports, December 1987-June 1990 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Documents and correspondence about Toronto. Material includes a Toronto Real Estate Market report, JJ Barnicke Limited Realtor yearly reports and other promotional material.
  - National Edge City Atlanta, March 1989-June 1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Newspaper articles about Atlanta and its surrounding regions. Articles include two articles from the Atlanta Business Chronicle "Southern Hospitality Thrives in North Atlanta" by David Jowers and Bill Gregory and "Long commutes worth it to residents of 'Penturbia'" by Chris Morris, a Wall Street Journal article "Small Businesses Blossom Near Atlanta" by Michael J. McCarthy and a Washington Post article "Plan to Move Georgia City's Landmark Lays Egg" by Holly Morris.
  - Local Edge City The Towns of Belmont and Kentlands, April-July 1990 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Documents about two planned communities, Belmont in Loudoun County, VA and Kentlands in Gaithersburg, MD. Material includes promotional folders for Belmont and Kentland, a business card for Marjorie Valin of Joseph Alfandre and Co., information pamphlets for Kentlands, a letter to Joel Garreay from Margie Valin and the April 1990 issue of Architecture.
  - Local Edge City Kentlands, May 1988-April 1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Publicity about the planned community Kentlands in Gaithersburg, MD and Belmont in Loudoun County, VA. Material includes seven articles from the Gaithersburg Gazette "Planned Kentlands development: new ideas for a community" by Deidre Cryor, "Kentlands work session set Oct. 26" by David Lim, "Fiscal realities of Kentlands discussed" by David Lim, "'Cultural campus' evolves at charrette" by David Lim, "Need for more parking at Kentlands debated" by David Lim, "A new way of planning", and "Residents affirm zoning limitation to Alfandre" by Healan Barrow, a Saturday Post-Courier article "Old Charleston inspires new communities" by J. Dean Foster, three Loudoun Times-Mirror articles "Village idea gains" by Michael C. Mahoney, "Planning consultant talks to board about 'vision'" by Otto Mayr, and "Board adopts Belmont concept", three Patuxent Publishing Company Free-Press articles "Residents scrutinize final design charrette" by Joel Davis, "Charrette debate extended by design" by Jim Joyner and "Stranger in Sandy Spring" by Jim Joyner and Joel Davis, a Daily Record article "Alfandre Palns Massive 19th Century Village" by Alexander Montague, a Potomac Almanac article "Developing 'Small-town' Air" by Judy Myers, three Gaithersburg Express articles "Alfandre wants public at Kentlands" by Mary Beth Smith, "What's in Kentlands' street name?" by Kenneth J. Rabben, "What is a charrette?" by Kenneth J. Rabben, and "Kentlands to focus on cultural heritage" by Kenneth J. Rabben, two Baltimore Sun articles "A New Traditionalism" by David Rosenthal and Edward Gunts and "They're Building Yesterday's Town for Today's Families" by Edward Gunts, a Washington Business Journal article "Architect leads push to turn back design" by Michael Cody, four Washington Post articles "Deigning Tomorrow's Community in a Week" by Cornelius F. Foote Jr., "Harking Back to Our Town" by Benjamin Forgey, "Designers Revive the Old With 'New Traditional Towns'" by Roger K. Lewis and "When Working by Committee Isn't All Bad" by Roger K. Lewis, two New York Times articles "In Seven Days, Designing a New Traditional Town" by Patricia Leigh Brown and "A Big Small Town Getting Under Way" by Alex Montague, a San Francisco Examiner article "Planning a city fit for human habitation" by Gary Delshohn, a Montgomery Journal article "Birth of An American Town" by Matt Hamblen, the January 1990 issue of Builder magazine, a Warfield's article "What Can Be Done To Save the Suburbs?" by Ralph Bennett, a Metropolitan Home Design article "The New Town Planners" by Andres Duany and Elizabeth Plater-Zyberk, a People magazine article "Banishing Cookie-Cutter 'Burbs", two Urban Land Institute publications about development trends and Kentlands, a Newsweek article "The House of the Future" by Jerry Adler, a U.S. News and World Report article "The Quest for Community" by Amy Saltzman and the April 1990 issue of Warfiled's Business Monthly.
  - Local Edge City Riviera, June 1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Documents about Riviera, a planned community in Charles County, MD. Material includes an executive summary of the Riviera community, a hand written note from James H. Burch and a list of measures to be taken for the Riviera community.
  - Local Edge City The Future of Arlington, November 1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    A publication about The Future of Arlington.
  - Local Edge City New Carrollton, August 1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    A Washington Post article about the construction of the New Carrollton, MD metro station.
  - Local Edge City Ft. Belvoir, December 1988 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    A Washington Post article about land development at Fort Belvoir in Fairfax, VA.
  - Edge City Skyline City, VA, November 1988 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    A Washington Post article about a group of highrise buildings in Fairfax County, VA.
  - Local Edge City Proposed Cascades, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    An advertisement for Cascades, a planned community in Vienna, VA.
  - National Edge City LA Times Magazine, January-March 1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Three copies of the January 15, 1989 issue of LA Times Magazine and a handwritten note to Joel Garreau.
  - National Edge City Los Angeles, October 1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Documents about Los Angeles. Material includes an article from the Economist about California, "The Evolution of Suburban Downtowns in Midwestern Metropolises" and "Land Use Change in Suburban Clusters and Corridors" by Thomas J. Baerwald.
  - National Edge City Los Angeles Market Reports, January 1987 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    A Los Angeles Real Estate Market Report.
  - National Edge City Los Angeles, August 1990-June 1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Documents about Los Angeles. Material includes notes, an outline of Edge Cities, maps of the Dallas, Houston, Phoenix, and Atlanta areas, an article about California mass transit systems and a Time magazine article about urbanization.
  - National Edge City Los Angeles Market Reports, March 1990 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Documents about Los Angeles. Material includes a Los Angeles Real Estate Market Real Estate reports and Los Angeles Metropolitan Area Market Opportunity Analysis.
  - National Edge City London Market Reports, September 1988, May 1990 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Two London Office Market Real Estate reports and an article about Docklands neighborhood of London.
  - Miscellaneous Foreign Edge Cities, Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Notes about foreign edge cities.
  - National Edge City Detroit Post Riot, July 1987 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    A Washington Post article about Detroit, MI twenty years after the race riots.
  - National Edge City Detroit, March 1987-February 1990 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Documents and correspondence about Detroit, MI. Material includes two articles from The Economist, the transcript of an interview of James Burke, a publication for The International Forum of the North American Seminar, a Washington Post and Wall Street Journal articles about Detroit, notes and "Sectoral Clustering and Metropolitan Development" by Edwin S. Mills from "Sources of Metropolitan Growth and Development".
  - National Edge City New York-Connecticut, December 1988 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    A market analysis and program recommendations for the proposed residential development at Westridge in Danbury, CT.
  - National Edge City New York New Jersey Metro Park, January-May 1989 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Information about Amtrak rail service. Material includes notes and the Northeast Corridor Services Winter/Spring 1989 Amtrak Train Timetables.
  - Edge City New York Jersey City, January-September 1989 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Pamphlets and brochures about New Jersey attractions. Material includes two booklets about the Statue of Liberty, a northern New Jersey regional guide and map, flyer for a Statue of Liberty Ferry line, a map of LIberty State Park, Statue of Liberty National Park Service brochure, the birds of Liberty State Park, interpretive programs at Liberty State Park, nature path at Liberty State Park, a newsletter from the Sci-Tech Center at Liberty State Park, a newsletter from the New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection, a newsletter from the Liberty State Park Development Corporation, a flyer for the 1989 New Jersey Ethnic Festival, a business card for Mona Olenek from Port Liberte, a New Jersey Transit rail schedule, a flyer for an exhibit at the Sci-Tech Center at Liberty State Park and a sheet of statistics for the Statue of Liberty.
  - National Edge City New York City Market Reports, January 1990 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    A notebook and other notes about New York City.
  - National Edge City Pasadena, December 1984-February 1988 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Documents and correspondence about Pasadena, CA. Material includes a brochure for museums of the Pasadena area, a Pasadena chamber of commerce resource book, a note book, a Pasadena promotional booklet, notes, Joel Garreau's business card, a Pasadena community development commission folder containing articles from the LA Times, LA Business Journal, National Real Estate Investor and Shopping Center World, a list of major office projects since 1974, a development update, a greater Los Angeles office marketing guide, selections from the October 1986 issue of The Atlantic, a visitors guide for Pasadena, business cards for William C. Reynolds of the City of Pasadena and Joel V. Sheldon III of Vroman's, an article from Pasadena Star News, a collection of Washington Post articles, a map of Pasadena, development promotion for northwest Pasadena and the Spring/Summer 1989 issue of Pasadena Development Quarterly.
  - National Edge City Philadelphia, August 1987-May 1991 (Box 3, Folder 2)